great deal, comrades. Did we not see for ourselves how he attempted, fortunately
without success, to get us defeated and destroyed at the Battle of the Cowshed?
The animals were stupefied.
This was a wickedness far outdoing Snowball's destruction of the windmill.
But it was some minutes before they could fully take it in.
They all remembered, or thought they remembered, how they had seen Snowball
charging ahead of them at the Battle of the Cowshed, how he had rallied and
encouraged them at every turn, and how he had not paused for an instant even
when the pellets from Jones's gun had wounded his back.
At first, it was a little difficult to see how this fitted in with his being on
Jones's side.
Even Boxer, who seldom asked questions, was puzzled.
He lay down, tucked his four hooves beneath him, shut his eyes, and with a
hard effort managed to formulate his thoughts.
>> I do not believe that.
Snowball fought bravely at the Battle of the Cowshed. I saw him myself.
Did we not give him Animal Hero First Class immediately afterwards?
>> That was our mistake, comrade, for we know now, it is all written down in the
secret documents that we have found, that in reality, he was trying to lure us to our doom.
>> But he was wounded.
We all saw him running with blood.
>> That was part of the arrangement.
Jones's shot only grazed him. I could show you this in his own writing if you
were able to read it. The plot was for Snowball at the critical moment to give
the signal for flight and leave the field to the enemy, and he very nearly
succeeded. I will even say, comrades, he would have succeeded if it had not been
for our heroic leader, comrade Napoleon.
Do you not remember how, just at the moment when Jones and his men had got
inside the yard, Snowball suddenly turned and fled, and many animals
followed him? And do you not remember too that it was just at that moment when
panic was spreading and all seemed lost that comrade Napoleon sprang forward
with a cry of death to humanity and sank his teeth in Jones's leg. Surely you
remember that comrades.
>> Exclaimed Squealer frisking from side to side.
Now when Squealer described the scenes so graphically, it seemed to the animals
that they did remember it.
At any rate, they remembered that at the critical moment of the battle, Snowball
had turned to flee.
But Boxer was still a little uneasy.
>> I do not believe that Snowball was a traitor at the beginning.
He said finally.
What he has done since is different.
But I believe that at the Battle of the Cowshed, he was a good comrade.
>> Our leader, comrade Napoleon, >> announced Squealer speaking very slowly and firmly.
Has stated categorically, categorically comrade, that Snowball was Jones's agent
from the very beginning. Yes, and from long before the rebellion was ever thought of.
>> Ah, that is different.
If comrade Napoleon says it, it must be right.
>> That is the true spirit comrade.
>> Cried Squealer.
But it was noticed he cast a very ugly look at Boxer with his little twinkling eyes.
He turned to go then paused and added impressively.
>> I warn every animal on this farm to keep